[Music]
imagine you happen across a short movie
script that describes a scene between a
person and their AI assistant the script
has what the person asks the AI but the
ai's response has been torn off suppose
you also have this powerful magical
machine that can take any text and
provide a sensible prediction of what
word comes next you could then finish
the script by feeding in what you have
to the machine seeing what it would
predict to start the ai's answer and
then repeating this over and over
with a growing script completing the
dialogue when you interact with a
chatbot this is exactly what's happening
a large language model is a
sophisticated mathematical function that
predicts what word comes next for any
piece of text instead of predicting one
word with certainty though what it does
is assign a probability to all possible
next words to build a chatbot what you
do is lay out some text that describes
an interaction between a user and a
hypothetical AI assistant you add on
whatever the user types in as the first
part of that interaction and then you
have the model repeatedly predict the
next word that such a hypothetical AI
assistant would say in response and
that's what's presented to the user in
doing this the output tends to look a
lot more natural if you allow it to
select less likely words along the way
at random so what this means is even
though the model itself is deterministic
a given prompt typically gives a
different answer each time it's run
models learn how to make these
predictions by processing an enormous
amount of text typically pulled from the
internet for a standard human to read
the amount of text that was used to
train gpt3 for example if they read
non-stop 24/7 it would take over 2600
years larger models since then train on
much much more you can think of training
a little bit like tuning the dials on a
big machine the way that a language
model behaves is entirely determined by
these many different continuous values
usually called parameters or weights
changing those parameters will change
the probabilities that the model gives
for the next word on a given input what
puts the large inlarge language model is
how they can have hundreds of billions
of these
parameters no human ever deliberately
sets those parameters instead they begin
at random meaning the model just outputs
gibberish but they're repeatedly refined
based on many example pieces of text one
of these training examples could be just
a handful of words
or it could be thousands but in either
case the way this works is to pass in
all but the last word from that example
into the model and compare the
prediction that it makes with the true
last word from the example an algorithm
called back propagation is used to tweak
all of the parameters in such a way that
it makes the model a little more likely
to choose the true last word and a
little less likely to choose all the
others when you do this for many many
trillions of examples not only does the
model start to give more accurate
predictions on the training data but it
also starts to make more reasonable
predictions on text that it's never seen
before given the huge number of
parameters and the enormous amount of
training data the scale of computation
involved in training a large language
model is
mindboggling to illustrate imagine that
you could perform 1 billion additions
and multiplications every single second
how long do you think that it would take
for you to do all of the operations
involved in training the largest
language models do you think it would
take a year maybe something like 10,000
years the answer is actually much more
than that it's well over 100 million
years this is only part of the story
though this whole process is called
pre-training the goal of autocompleting
a random passage of text from the
Internet is very different from the goal
of being a good AI assistant to address
this chatbots undergo another type of
training just as important called
reinforcement learning with human
feedback workers flag unhelpful or
problematic predictions and their
Corrections further change the model's
parameters making them more likely to
give predictions that users prefer
looking back at the pre-training though
this staggering amount of computation is
only made possible by using special
computer chips that are optimized for
running many many operations in parallel
known as gpus however not all language
models models can be easily parallelized
prior to 2017 most language models would
process text one word at a time but then
a team of researchers at Google
introduced a new model known as the
Transformer Transformers don't read text
from the start to the Finish they soak
it all in at once in parallel the very
first step inside a Transformer and most
other language models for that matter is
to associate each word with a long list
of numbers the reason for this is that
the training process only works with
continuous values so you have to somehow
encode language using numbers and each
of these list of numbers May somehow
encode the meaning of the corresponding
word what makes Transformers unique is
their Reliance on a special operation
known as attention this operation gives
all of these lists of numbers a chance
to talk to one another and refine the
meanings that they encode based on the
context around all done in parallel for
example the numbers encoding the word
Bank might be changed based on the
context surrounding it to somehow encode
the more specific notion of a river bank
Transformers typically also include a
second type of operation known as a
feedforward neural network and this
gives the model extra capacity to store
more patterns about language learned
during training all of this data
repeatedly flows through many different
iterations of these two fundamental
operations and as it does so the hope is
that each list of numbers is enriched to
code whatever information might be
needed to make an accurate prediction of
what word follows in the passage at the
end one final function is performed on
the last Vector in this sequence which
now has had a chance to be influenced by
all the other context from the input
text as well as everything the model
learned during training to produce a
prediction of the next word again the
model's prediction looks like a
probability for every possible next
word although researchers design the
framework for how each of these steps
work it's important to understand that
the specific behavior is an emergent
phenomenon based on how those hundreds
of billions of parameters are tuned
during training this makes it incredibly
challenging to determine why the model
makes the exact predictions that it does
what you can see is that when you use
large language model predictions to
autocomplete a prompt the words that it
generates are uncannily fluent
fascinating and even useful
[Music]
if you're a new viewer and you're
curious about more details on how
Transformers and attention work boy do I
have some material for you one option is
to jump into a series I made about deep
learning where we visualize and motivate
the details of attention and all the
other steps in a Transformer but also on
my second Channel I just posted a talk
that I gave a couple months ago about
this topic for the company TNG in Munich
sometimes I actually prefer the content
that I make as a casual talk rather than
a produced video but I leave it up to
you which one of these feels like the
better follow on
[Music]